Guide to the IBM European Business Archive ca. 1915-1960 (bulk 1933-1945) MSS.126
Fales Library and Special Collections
IBM European Business Archive
circa 1910-1960
1933-1945
Fales Library and Special Collections
International Business Machines Corporation
MSS.126
6 Linear Feet in 14 boxes.
The IBM European Business Archive contains administrative and legal materials documenting the relationship between IBM and its subsidiaries in Germany, with the bulk of the materials deriving from 1933-1945. Much of the remainder of the collection relates to IBM's subsequent efforts to regain shareholder control of its German subsidiaries and machines after Allied victory.
Arrangement
The IBM European Business Archive is organized alphabetically by broad subject headings reflecting the original arrangement of the IBM corporate archives. The collection is arranged into three series, retaining the series arrangement it had when it arrived at Fales from IBM Corporate Archives, via the Skirball Department of Hebrew and Judaic Studies at NYU. New arrangement schemes have only been imposed when large files contained tabbed subfolders, when a volume or pamphlet required its own folder, or when delicate or oversized material demanded removal from the original order.
Series I: European Office Records
Series II: Legal Records
Series III: Ledgers
Oversize - Series I: European Office Records
Historical Note
International Business Machines Corporation was incorporated in New York State on June 16, 1911 under the name Computing-Tabulating-Recording Co. In 1922, Computing-Tabulating-Recording Co. purchased all of the shares of Deutsche Hollerith Maschinen Gesellschaft. In 1924 the official name of the company was changed to International Business Machines Corporation. In 1933, IBM CEO Thomas Watson ordered the merger of IBM subsidiaries in Germany (Optima, Degemag, Holgemag, Dehomag) under the name Dehomag, granting the company rights to sell Hollerith punch-card machines throughout Europe.
Scope and Content
The IBM European Business Archive contains materials related to the functioning of IBM and its German subsidiaries, with an emphasis on documents produced during and after World War II. At the folder level, materials cover a large date range, often from the early inter-war period to the early nineteen-sixties.
The most frequently occurring name in the collection is Willy Heidinger, creator of the firm Deutsche Hollerith Maschinen Gesellschaft (AKA DHMG or Dehomag). DHMG was a corporation devoted to the manufacture and sale of electronic punch-card devices for census use in Europe; it was eventually incorporated by IBM in 1933. The majority of the documents in series I and II refer to contested capital restructuring agreements between Heidinger and principal parties in German and American offices of IBM. Others involved in these disputes include Karl Humell and Hermann Rottke, Dehomag directors who received "loans" from IBM NY to give the appearance of compliance with the Third Reich's "Germanization" policies. These loan agreements are referenced in documents including Photostat copies of correspondence, original telegrams, and transcripts of phone conversations and other communication. Many of the documents are present in both German and English versions.
After the war, IBM engaged in recouping all of its Dehomag assets that had been displaced during the war. Attorney Harrison Chauncey, a chief negotiator for IBM NY, is represented here by travel documents, telegrams, and correspondence describing his visits to Germany to negotiate settlements between IBM and Dehomag representatives. Newspaper clippings and other ephemera appear inter alia, in their original context.
Accounting procedures for Dehomag are represented in Series III by general ledgers from 1933-1938 from three IBM Germany components (Optima, Gegemag and Dehomag). Series I contains extensive documentation of IBM's European assets as of the immediate post-war period, including investment recovery data, annual reports, account statements, auditors' reports, and location of rental machines in Europe.
SOURCES:
Black, E. (2001). IBM and the Holocaust: The strategic alliance between Nazi Germany and America's most powerful corporation. New York: Crown.
International Business Machines, Corp. In Business & Company Resource Center. Retrieved July 24, 2009, from http://galenet.galegroup.com/servlet/ BCRC?vrsn=unknown&locID=nysl_me_tnypl&srchtp=glbc&cc=1&c=1&mode=c&ste=60&tbst=tsCM&tab=1&ccmp=International+Business+Machines+Corp.&mst=IBM&n=25&bConts=13311&ses=1
Dillard, J. (2003, Fall2003). "Professional Services, IBM, and the Holocaust." Journal of Information Systems, 17(2), 1-16. Retrieved July 24, 2009, from Business Source Premier database.
Provenance
The materials were given by the IBM Corporate Archives on "short-term loan" to NYU's Skirball Department of Hebrew and Judaic Studies in 1999. In 2001 the collection was officially donated and transferred to the Fales Library and Special Collections.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Holocaust.; Business records.; Ledgers (account books); Germany.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Germany.; Legal documents.; Gegemag; Ingemag; Optima; Heidinger, Willy; Chauncey, Harrison; Degemag; Watson, Thomas John, 1874-1956; Rottke, Hermann; Hummel, Karl
- Series I: European Office Records
  Scope and Content note
  SERIES I: European Office Records is composed of office records, grouped alphabetically by subject headings. The bulk of this series is devoted to financial correspondence between the IBM office in New York and IBM subsidiaries in Germany, including Degemag, Dehomag and Optima.
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: Auditor's Report Dated May 10, 1947 on an Examination of the Accounts at December 31, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: Auditor's Report, 1948, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: Auditor's Report Dated May 15, 1949 on an Examination of the Tentative Accounts at June, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: Auditor's Report Dated June 20, 1950, on an Examination of the Tentative Accounts at December 31, 1949, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: Auditor's Reports of 1950, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: Balance Sheets, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: Correspondence Related to IBM Property Other Than Dehomag, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: Correspondence Related to Recovery of Possession and Control of IBM Interests in Germany, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: Dehomag Account Statements - IBM Offices Outside Germany, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: Dehomag Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: Dehomag Tax Situation, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: Directors, Officers, Principal Managers of Dehomag as on December 31, 1946, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: Explanations as to Comparative Balance Sheet and Statement of Proofit and Loss, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: List of Plants, Sales, and Administrative Offices of Dehomag, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: Material for the Calculation of Value of Minority Interest: Heidinger, Hummel, Rottke (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: Pre-War Rental Equipment, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: Registration of American-Owned Property, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: Report on Dehomag Operating Methods, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Conditions as of December 31, 1946: Stockholders of Dehomag, Documents Related to Capital Correction, 1941-1947 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Decontrol of IBM Interests in Germany, 1947-1951 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Hummel and Rottke Loan Accounts - Divident Prepaid to Heidinger, 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Inter-Company Account (1 of 2), 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Inter-Company Account (2 of 2), 1948-1951 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Inter-Company Account Reconciliations, 1940-1942 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - International Business Machines Corporation, New York: General Report and Enclosures 1-4, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - International Business Machines Corporation, New York: General Report Enclosure, 5-7, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Investment Recovered, 1948-1953 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Investment Recovery Data (1 of 4), 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Investment Recovery Data (2 of 4), 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Investment Recovery Data (3 of 4), 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Investment Recovery Data (4 of 4), 1946-1949 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Investment Recovery Data/Investment Analysis, 1939-1949 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - National Region Trade Council, Inc. (1 of 2), 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - National Region Trade Council, Inc. (2 of 2), 1948-1951 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - New York Goods Account Statement, 1940-1951 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Rental Machines, 1945-1950 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Reports to Military Authorities, 1945-1947 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Saar Territory, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Special Reports-New York, 1945-1957 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Series II: Legal Records
  SERIES II: Legal Records is composed of Legal Records containing documentary evidence of transactions between IBM and its subsidiaries, including telephone transcripts, telegrams and letters.
  - Annual Report: "Deutsche Bank und Disconto-Gesellschaft", 1933 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bulletins, Opinions, Revelations, Correspondence, 1932-1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Capitalization and Incorporation: Degemag, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Capitalization and Incorporation: "Gesellschaft für Geschaftmaschinen", 1910-1951 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Capitalization and Incorporation: Ingemag, 1910-1951 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Capitalization and Incorporation: "New" Dehomag, 1910-1951 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Capitalization and Incorporation: "Old" Dehomag, 1910-1951 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Capitalization and Incorporation: Optima, 1910-1951 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Heidinger, et al, Shareholdings, 1940-1955 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence and Phone Conversations: Chauncey, Heidinger Share Transfer, 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    IBM European Business Archive
    The IBM European Business Archive is arranged alphabetically within three series, as the collection appeared when it arrived at Fales. New arrangement schemes have only been imposed when large files contained tabbed subfolders, when a volume or pamphlet required its own folder, or when delicate or oversized material demanded separation from the original order.
    SERIES I is composed of European Office Records, grouped alphabetically by subject headings. The bulk of this series is devoted to financial correspondence between the IBM office in New York and IBM subsidiaries in Germany, including Degemag, Dehomag and Optima.
    SERIES II is composed of Legal Records containing documentary evidence of transactions between IBM and its subsidiaries, including telephone transcripts, telegrams and letters.
    SERIES III comprises business ledgers from IBM Germany: Degemag, Dehomag and Optima.
  - Correspondence Related to Shareholdings, 1922-1957 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Dividend Policy (Willy Heidinger): Correspondence, 1914-1938 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Financial Statements, Reports and Correspondence: Dehomag (1 of 3), 1940-1948 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Financial Statements, Reports and Correspondence: Dehomag (2 of 3), 1940-1948 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Financial Statements, Reports and Correspondence: Dehomag (3 of 3), 1914-1939 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Incorporation: Bylaws and Charter: Degemag, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Incorporation: Bylaws and Charter: Gesellschaft fur Geschaftsmaschinen, 1910-1958 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Incorporation: Bylaws and Charter: Gesellschaft fur Geschaftsmaschinen - Bundesgesetzblatt, 1910-1958 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Incorporation: Bylaws and Charter: Ingemag, 1910-1959 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Incorporation: Bylaws and Charter: "New" Dehomag, 1910-1958 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Incorporation: Bylaws and Charter: "Old" Dehomag, 1910-1959 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Incorporation: Bylaws and Charter: Optima, 1910-1959 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Incorporation: Correspondence Re: Mergers, 1932-1938 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Incorporation: Documents Related to Corporate Name Change, 1934-1960 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Incorporation: General Correspondence, 1934-1960 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Incorporation: Merger Documents (English Translation), 1910-1941 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Incorporation: Merger Documents (German Text), 1910-1941 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Loan Agreement, Miscellaneous Documents (Karl Hummel, Willy Heidinger, Hermann Rottke), 1937-1953 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Machines: Customer Engineering Service, U.S. Military Installations, 1946-1950 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Machines: "Der Rechenlocher Type II" Publication, c. 1945 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Machines, Manufacturing and Shipping: Documents and Correspondence, 1935-1950 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Minutes of the Regular Shareholders' Meetings, 1934-1960 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1941-1968 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Documents, Reports on Business Travel: (Harrison K. Chauncey), 1940-1948 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Price Lists and Related Correspondence (1 of 2), 1938-1948 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Price Lists and Related Correspondence (2 of 2) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Rental Machines: Documents and Correspondence, 1935-1950 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Rottke, Hermann: Loan Agreement, 1937-1953 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Share Transfer Drafts: Heidinger, et al., 1937-1953 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Shareholdings: Documentary Evidence (Exhibits 1-7), 1922-1958 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Shareholdings: Documentary Evidence (Exhibits 8-16), 1922-1958 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Shareholdings: Documentary Evidence: "Gesellschaft fur Elektrische Unternehmungen Aktiengesellschaft" Annual Report, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Shareholdings: Documentary Evidence: Unexecuted Affidavit, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Shareholdings: Documentary Evidence, Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Taxes and Related Correspondence, 1932-1967 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Trademark Agreement: Electromatic Typewriters and Mercedes Euromaschinen-Werke Aktiengesellschaft, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Trademarks and Copyrights, 1914-1958 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Series III: Ledgers
  SERIES III: Ledgers comprises business ledgers from IBM Germany: Degemag, Dehomag and Optima. Due to the deterioration of the bindings of the ledgers, their pages have been removed and housed in folders.
  - Degemag 1933 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Degemag 1934 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Germany Degemag 1935 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Germany Degemag 1936 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Degemag 1937 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Degemag 1938 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Dehomag 1933 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Dehomag 1934 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Germany Dehomag 1935 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Germany Dehomag 1936 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Dehomag 1937 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Dehomag 1938 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Optima 1933 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Optima 1934 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Germany Optima 1935 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Germany Optima 1936 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Optima 1937 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Optima 1938 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Oversize - Series I: European Office Records
  The Oversize series consists of a small number of documents that had originally been folded and stored in legal-sized folders.
  - Incorporation: Bylaws and Charter: Ingemag District Court in Charlottenburg, Certified Copy from the Commercial Register, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Physical Inventory of Electric Bookkeeping and Accounting Machines, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Statements of Assets and Liabilities at December 31, 1949 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Statement of Unfilled Stock Orders, 1934 (Box 14, Folder 4)